Andy Rubin, head of Google's Android team in 2013,
famously defined Android's openness with this Tweet, offering the
instructions for downloading and building the Android source code.
As app developers, it's handy to be able to peep
behind the curtains and see how the framework actually
works. And it's an excellent way to find answers to
tricky, Stack Overflow questions. But the Android Open Source
Project, or AOSP as its commonly known, is much more
than that. The source code is available under the
Apache 2 license, so anyone can take it and do
anything they want with it, including modifying it and redistributing
it. And they have. Android has always had a passionate
community of modders, from Steve Kondik and the Cyanogen community
to XDA and many others who have been distributing modified
images of Android for phone owners brave enough to try
them. Even big companies like Amazon have taken the Android
source code and modified it for use in their own
line of products. That openness extends to the apps themselves, the
AOSP includes key mobile apps like the dialer, app launcher,
calendar, and email. And Google offers it own versions of each
as well. In the early days those native apps were
tightly bound to the framework and could only get updated along
with the platform. Which admittedly in the early days seemed like
every few weeks. But as the time between platform releases grew,
so did the efforts to unbundle those apps, allowing
them to be updated through Google Play. That was great
news for users, but it had an even better
side effect for us developers. Because apps like Gmail and
Maps depend on a number of proprietary Google APIs,
Google released Google Play Services. Also code named after food
to support the Google apps, while also giving us
developers Google specific APIs, like Maps, Wallet, Drive, and YouTube.
So now we get the latest and greatest Google specific APIs
every six weeks or so. And rather than being tied to
a specific platform, they're available on every device, back to Gingerbread.
Oh, and of course every native app is also entirely replaceable.
So you can publish apps to replace any of the apps
shipped with the device. And we can build our own SMS
apps, homescreens or maps apps, publish it on Play and give
users the choice to make it their default. When Android was first
announced, Andy Rubin described the AOSP as, all the software
to run a mobile phone but without the proprietary obstacles
that have hindered mobile innovation. Today, Android runs on more
than just mobiles, but the core of its purpose remains
the same. A platform and ecosystem that allows models, carriers,
OEMs and app developers to innovate and compete. So, armed
with an open, evolving platform enriched by a growing set
of Google API's and the ability to create great apps
that let users customize every aspect of
their user experience, you can use other people's
work to help define the computing platform of
the future. And that's my definition of open.